National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection AFC 2004/007
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection 1997-2009
AFC 2004/007
National Visionary Leadership Project
33 boxes
transcripts: 15 v.: col. ill.; 22 cm.
288 transcripts, unbound
manuscripts, 4 folders
1026 videocassettes (Betacam, DVCAM, Mini-DV): sound, color, various sizes
7 videocassettes (VHS): sound, color.
12 video discs (CD-ROM): sound, color.
artifact: 1 medal
868 photographs prints: color; 4 x 6.
3351 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
The National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection consists primarily of master recordings of interviews by the National Visionary Leadership Project with significant figures in 20th century African American history. In addition, the collection includes transcripts (both printed and electronic) of a portion of the interviews, edited versions of the interviews and print and digital photographs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Cosby, Camille O. (Camille Olivia), 1944- interviewer.; Poussaint, Renee, interviewer.
Organizations
American Folklife Center, sponsor.; Archive of Folk Culture (Library of Congress); National Visionary Leadership Project, collector.; Summit on the State of Black America (2003: Library of Congress)
Subjects
African American actors--Interviews.; African American artists--Interviews.; African American athletes--Interviews.; African American authors--Interviews.; African American businesspeople--Interviews.; African American civil rights workers--Interviews.; African American clergy--Interviews.; African American college teachers--Interviews.; African American dancers--Interviews.; African American educators--Interviews.; African American journalists--Interviews.; African American lawyers--Interviews.; African American leadership.; African American legislators--Interviews.; African American musicians--Interviews.; African American physicians--Interviews.; African American scientists--Interviews.; African American veterans--Interviews.; African American women--Interviews.; African Americans--Biography.; African Americans--Education.; African Americans--Employment.; African Americans--History--20th century.; African Americans--Politics and government.; African Americans--Religion.; African Americans--Social life and customs.; Civil rights movements--United States--History--20th century.
Titles
Title on container: National Visionary Leadership Project; Summit on the state of black America, 2003.; Visionary interview excerpts.
Form/Genre
Digital photographs--Color--2000-2010.; Filmed interviews.; Interviews.; Oral histories.; Transcripts.; Videocassettes.
Administrative Information
Provenance
The National Visionary Leadership Project collection was donated in seven accruals between 2004 and 2010.
Accruals
Further accruals are expected to this collection.
Bibliograpahy
Edited versions of some interviews produced by NVLP can be accessed at their website: http://www.visionaryproject.org
Edited versions of 47 interviews were published in: Cosby, Camille O. and Renee Poussaint. A Wealth of Wisdom: Legendary African American Elders Speak. New York: Washington Square Press, 2004.
Access and Restrictions
The collection is open for research use. Access restrictions apply. Please contact the Folklife Reading Room before requesting materials: http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact Consult reference staff in the Folklife Reading Room about reference copies of material and additional reference tools that may be available onsite only. The original moving image videos are stored at the Packard Campus of the National Audio-Visual Conservation Center. Digitized copies may be viewed in the Folklife Reading Room. Duplication of the collection materials is governed by copyright and other restrictions. Permission of the rights holder may need to be obtained. Please refer to the AFC web site for information on ordering copies of unpublished recordings (http://www.loc.gov/folklife/recordering.html) and photographic materials (http://www.loc.gov/folklife/photo_ordering.html).
Digital and Physical Copies
Digital and physical materials were received as part of the records of the National Visionary Leadership Project. Transcripts donated as MS Word files have print copies. Both digital and print photographs were received as original materials; some may be copies. All digital photographs were printed on black and white paper and are filed with the original print color photographs. All moving images formats except for VHS were digitized. The original moving image videos are stored at the Packard Campus of the National Audio-Visual Conservation Center. Digitized copies may be viewed in the Folklife Reading Room.
Administrative History
In 2001 Camille Cosby and Renee Pouissant founded the National Visionary Leadership Project (NVLP) to document the work and lives of African Americans in the United States as a way to preserve and disseminate their knowledge and insights. The NVLP was headquartered in Washington, D.C., and conducted educational programs and outreach, oral history projects and intergenerational events. This collection is comprised of full-length interviews made for the NVLP of prominent or influential African Americans. The interviews were conducted by Camille O. Cosby, Renee Poussaint or a Visionary Heritage Fellow. Some interviews are disseminated via online streaming at the NVLP website: http://www.visionaryproject.org.
The NVLP created the Visionary Heritage Fellowship Program to promote education in African American history and the participation of college students in the preservation of this history. It was a competitive one-year fellowship, open to all students in the United States. Each fellow attended a conference the summer before the start of their academic fellow year where they learned interview techniques and basic video production, among other topics. In order to apply for the program, the fellowship candidate had to chose a person who they believed was a visionary. This visionary had to be at least 70 years old and have made a “significant contribution in their field and in the African American community.” These fellowship interviews were then deposited with NVLP, where they became a permanent part of the Visionary collection. Additional information on the NVLP, or the Visionary Heritage Fellowship Program, can be found at http://www.visionaryproject.org.
The NVLP also promoted grass-roots production of African American oral history through its Legacy Guide. This publication encourages the creation of oral histories with the intent that they be donated to libraries and museums. These interviews are not included in this collection.
NVLP has hosted the Summit on the State of Black America four times at the Library of Congress. The Summits engaged an audience of college and high school students in problem-solving discussions with a panel comprised of nationally-known visionary elders and college students, participants in NVLP’s Visionary Heritage Fellows Program. Together they developed solutions to contemporary issues in the African American community. NVLP has also hosted other panel discussions called “A Legacy of Change,” and sponsored the Wisdom Awards Ceremonies to honor visionaries.
Scope and Content Note
The NVLP collection at the Library of Congress consists of 996 master video recordings of 301 interviews, 288 transcripts, 3351 digital photographs and 863 print photographs. In addition, the collection includes a small amount of promotional materials, items from the 2003 and 2007 Summit on the State of Black America event, and a medal. Of the interviews that have been transcribed, 15 have bound copies.
These interviews vary widely in length and subject. Most transcripts contain biographical information for the interviewees. All the interviewees are considered elders who have lived the majority of their lives in the 20th century. Persons interviewed include educators, scientists, authors, community activists, doctors, entertainers, artists and politicians. They represent many different geographical areas, educational levels and economic statuses. Many of the interviewees are well-known, including Shirley Chisholm, Dick Gregory, Coretta Scott King, Odetta, Gordon Parks, and Faith Ringgold. Others, such as Willie T. Barrow, Pecolia Boyles, Jayme Coleman, and McDonald Williams, were not nationally known, but were influential within their own community or region. Approximately 40 interviewees were civil rights organizers or activists in the 1950s and 1960s, many of which made major contributions to the movement but are not well known figures.
The master recordings were done in a multiple of formats, primarily BetaCamSP, but also include MiniDV60 and DV Cam 64. Some of the interviews also have an accompanying edited version, primarily stored on DVCam 184 or DV 186 formats. Five of the interviews have been edited for presentation copies, which are on VHS. These interviewees are: Edward Brooke, Cardiss Collins, David Dinkins, John Hope Franklin, and Dorothy Height (two copies). These five visionaries were honored at the Summit on the State of Black America, an NVLP sponsored event at the Library of Congress in 2003. A VHS recording of the event is included with the preservation copies of these interviewees. Promotional DVDs with clips of 24 interviews are also included as well as the printed and bound transcripts, some of which have CD inserts, of interviews conducted with Edward Brooke, Roscoe Lee Browne, Ray Charles, Cardiss Collins, Ossie Davis and Ruby Dee, David Dinkins, Katherine Dunham, Samuel L. Gravely, John Hope Franklin, Dorothy Height, John H. Johnson, Coretta Scott King, Constance Baker Motley and Gordon Parks.
Arrangement of the Records
The collection is arranged in three series: Administrative; Conferences and Events; and Interviews. The interviews are arranged by ID number assigned by accrual (see also the index of interviewees by last name). The bulk of the collection includes moving image interviews conducted from 1997-2009, many of which are accompanied by a transcript and photographs from the interview.
http://lccn.loc.gov/2004695153
Container List
- Series I: Administrative
  - Finding aid (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Report, "The First Five Years" (Box-folder 1/2)
  - News article, 2007 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Promotional materials, 2002-2006, 2 binders (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Legacy guide (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Visionary interview excerpts CD and informational DVD, 3 CD/DVD copies
- Series II: Conferences and Events
  - Summit on the State of Black America, 2003-05-14
    The Summit on the State of Black America at the Library of Congress honored five visionaries from the areas of politics, education, and social activism. The five honorees were Edward Brooke, Cardiss Collins, David Dinkins, John Hope Franklin and Dorothy Height. Moderated by veteran journalist Bernard Shaw, the audience consisted mainly of students from various colleges and high schools. The two hour program was divided into the subject areas of politics, economics and education.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655304
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (VHS) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master
  - Visionary Leadership Awards Ceremony and Intergenerational Summit on the State of Black America, 2006-02-22
    - Manuscripts, 3 programs (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Wisdom Awards and Intergenerational Summit on the State of Black America, 2007-10-16
    - Manuscripts, 1 program (Box-folder 1/7)
    - Artifacts, 1 medal (Box 33)
  - Collection donation event at Library of Congress, 2007
    - Graphic Images, 14 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 1/8)
- Series III: Interviews
  - Joe Adams oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2003-06-11, AFC 2004/007: 001
    Joe Adams was an actor and Ray Charles' manager and promoter.
    The interview includes Joe Adams' memories of growing up in Watts, California, joining the air force, and his early career as a radio DJ and actor. He recalls acting in Broadway plays, working for NBC and hosting shows in Las Vegas, Nevada. He discusses working for his friend Ray Charles as his manager, promoter and assistant.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655531
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (52 pages) (Box-folder 2/9)
    - Graphic Images, 19 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/323)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (Betacam SP) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 001.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 001.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 001.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 001.MV.004
  - Clifford Alexander oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2006-09-26, AFC 2004/007: 002
    Clifford Alexander was an advisor to President Lyndon Johnson on civil rights and the Voting Rights Act of 1965, chairman of Equal Employment Opportunity Commission, a law professor, and the first African-American Secretary of the Army.
    The interview includes Clifford Alexander's memories of growing up in New York City, his education at Harvard and Yale and his early career as an assistant district attorney. He describes working as an assistant to President Lyndon Johnson on civil rights issues, his work on the Equal Opportunity Employment Commission and as Secretary of the Army, and his unsuccessful run for mayor of Washington, D.C. He also includes his opinions on minorities in government, affirmative action, and current politics.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655451
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (64 pages) (Box-folder 2/10)
    - Graphic Images, 61 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/324)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (DVCAM) (256 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 002.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 002.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 002.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 002.MV.004
  - Maya Angelou oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2002-03-22, AFC 2004/007: 003
    Maya Angelou was a poet, memoirist, actress and director.
    The interview includes Maya Angelou's memories of becoming mute as a child and the mentorship of her teacher Mrs. Flowers, who encouraged her to read poetry. She recalls her relationships with her grandmother and brother and becoming a teenage mother. She discusses touring Europe while performing in "Porgy and Bess," writing the poem delivered at President Clinton's inauguration, and her participation in the civil rights movement.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655518
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (39 pages) (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Graphic Images, 16 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 16 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/325)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (Betacam SP) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 003.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 003.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 003.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 003.MV.004
  - Lee Archer oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2002-03-12, AFC 2004/007: 004
    Lee Archer was a Tuskegee Airman, Lieutenant Colonel in the U.S. Air Force and businessman.
    The interview includes Lee Archer's memories of growing up in Harlem, New York and joining the army to serve during World War II. He recalls training at a segregated base in Macon, Georgia, where he met his wife and training in Tuskegee to become a pilot. He discusses serving in Italy and performing bombing raids in Germany, attending college and law school, and his career at General Foods and Beatrice Foods.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655519
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (73 pages) (Box-folder 2/12)
    - Graphic Images, 4 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in. (Box-folder 25/326)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 004.MV.006
  - Ernie Banks oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-06-07, AFC 2004/007: 005
    Ernie Banks was a baseball player for the Kansas City Monarchs and the Chicago Cubs.
    The interview includes Ernie Banks' memories of growing up in Wylie, Texas, playing semi-professional baseball as a teenager and joining the army. He recalls playing in the Negro Leagues with Kansas City Monarchs and the difficulties of travelling through segregated areas. He discusses his friendships with Buck O'Neil and Jackie Robinson, meeting his wife, and becoming the first African American to play for the Chicago Cubs.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655561
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (89 pages) (Box-folder 2/13)
    - Graphic Images, 5 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/327)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 005.MV.007
  - Willie T. Barrow oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-07-13, AFC 2004/007: 006
    Rev. Dr. Willie Barrow was a minister at the Langley Avenue Church of God in Chicago, a civil rights activist and field organizer for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) and helped organize Operation BREADBASKET, Operation PUSH and the Rainbow PUSH Coalition.
    The interview includes Willie Barrow's memories of her childhood in rural Texas, attending the Pacific-Warner Theological Seminary in Portland, Oregon and her marriage to her husband Clyde. She recalls her career as a youth pastor in Chicago, her involvement in the labor movement, and her work as a field organizer for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC) including the Selma to Montgomery March of 1965. She also discusses her relationships with Jesse Jackson and Martin Luther King, Jr., her faith, and her work with Operation PUSH and as an AIDS activist.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655452
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (41 pages) (Box-folder 2/14)
    - Graphic Images, 30 photographs: color; 4 x 6 in.; 30 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/328)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 006.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 006.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 006.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 006.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 006.MV.005
  - Derrick Bell oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2005-06-22, AFC 2004/007: 007
    Derrick Bell was a lawyer at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund in the 1960s, deputy director of the Office for Civil Rights in the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and law professor at Harvard University, University of Oregon and New York University.
    The interview includes Derrick Bell's memories of growing up in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania and attending Duquesne University and University of Pittsburgh Law School. He discusses working on several school desegregations cases with Thurgood Marshall at the NAACP Legal Defense Fund and his resignations from Harvard and the University of Oregon over discriminatory hiring practices. He also discusses his opinions on affirmative action and current politics.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655453
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (65 pages) (Box-folder 2/15)
    - Graphic Images, 111 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/329)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (DVCAM) (192 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 007.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 007.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 007.MV.003
  - Lerone Bennett oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-04-27, AFC 2004/007: 008
    Lerone Bennett was a historian, journalist and editor who worked for Jet and Ebony.
    The interview includes Lerone Bennett's memories of growing up in Mississippi, working for black newspapers as a teenager, and attending Morehouse College. He recalls reporting for the Atlanta Daily World and moving to Chicago to write for Jet Magazine. He discusses his interest in African American history, editing Ebony Magazine and covering the civil rights movement.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655542
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (68 pages) (Box-folder 2/16)
    - Graphic Images, 12 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/330)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 008.MV.006
  - David Blackwell oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-05-22, AFC 2004/007: 009
    David Blackwell was a statistician and professor of mathematics.
    The interview includes David Blackwell's memories of growing up in Illinois and studying math at the University of Illinois and the Institute of Advanced Study. He recalls teaching at several black colleges, becoming chair of the mathematics department Howard University, and accepting a position at the University of California at Berkeley, where he taught for over 30 years. He discusses his teaching methods, research in statistics, the racism he faced in academia and being the first African-American elected to the Academy of Sciences.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655567
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (62 pages) (Box-folder 2/17)
    - Graphic Images, 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/331)
    - Moving Images, 5 videocassettes of 5 (Betacam SP) (150 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 009.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 009.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 009.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 009.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 009.MV.005
  - Randolph Bromery oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-11-17, AFC 2004/007: 010
    Randolph Bromery was a geologist and university administrator.
    The interview includes Randolph Bromery's memories of growing up in Cumberland, Maryland, joining the army and serving as a Tuskegee Airman. He recalls majoring in math at Howard University, living in Washington, D.C., and working at the U.S. Geological Survey. He discusses earning his Ph.D. in geology at Johns Hopkins University and his career at the University of Massachusetts, where he became chancellor and acquired the W.E.B. DuBois papers.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655532
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (121 pages) (Box-folder 2/18)
    - Graphic Images, 47 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 25/332)
    - Moving Images, 8 videocassettes of 8 (Betacam SP) (240 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.007; AFC 2004/007: 010.MV.008
  - Edward Brooke oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2001-10-31, AFC 2004/007: 011
    Edward Brooke was a lawyer, Attorney General of Massachusetts, and Republican Senator from Massachusetts.